Guide to the Nina Berberova Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Vladislav Khodasevich Papers, 1921-1939; Series VIII; 0.50' (1 box)
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Goleshnikov-Kutuzov, I.N., 1935-36 (Box 57, Folder 1291)
    - Golovina, Alla, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1292)
    - Gorky, Maxim, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1293)
    - Gorlin, Michel Gorlina, Raisa, 1936 May 30 (Box 57, Folder 1294)
    - Gusev, D., 1927, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1295)
    - Hofmann, M., 1934 (Box 57, Folder 1296)
    - Ivanov, Georgii, 1937, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1297)
    - Ivanov, Viacheslav, 1924-25, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1298)
    - Karpovich, Michael, 1926-35 (Box 57, Folder 1299)
    - Kuprin, Aleksandr Ivanovich (Box 57, Folder 1300)
    - Levinson, André, 1932 (Box 57, Folder 1301)
    - Lifar, Serge, 1936 (Box 57, Folder 1302)
    - Maklin, I., 1937 (Box 57, Folder 1303)
    - Merezhkovsky, Dmitry Sergeyevich, 1926-27 (Box 57, Folder 1304)
    - Petrovskaia, Nina, 1922-28, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1305)
    - Raevskii, Nikolai Alekseevich, 1938 (Box 57, Folder 1306)
    - Remizov, Aleksei, 1933 (Box 57, Folder 1307)
    - Robakidze, Grigol, 1934 (Box 57, Folder 1308)
    - Rogovenko-Aksaiskii, ----, 1937 Sep 29 (Box 57, Folder 1309)
    - Rudnev, V., 1934 Jul 25 (Box 57, Folder 1310)
    - Segodnia, 1936 Oct 29 (Box 57, Folder 1311)
    - Shapovalenko, N.G., 1935 Oct 23 (Box 57, Folder 1312)
    - Shengeli, Georgii, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1313)
    - Smolenskii, Vladimir, 1937, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1314)
    - Soiuz russkikh pisatelei i zhurnalistov, 1938 Jan 26 (Box 57, Folder 1315)
    - Sologub, Fedor, 1922 (Box 57, Folder 1316)
    - Struve, Gleb, 1923-36 (Box 57, Folder 1317)
    - TSvetaeva, Marina Ivanovna, 1933-37, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1318)
    - Veber, Evgenii, 1933-34 (Box 57, Folder 1319)
    - Unidentified, 1933-37, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1320)
      Includes letters from Ivan Kologrivov and from A. Semenov.
      Includes a typescript letter from Vladislav Khodasevich to Ilia Fondaminskii.
  - WRITINGS
    - "Pamiati V.A. Piasta," (article), typescript, 1931 (Box 57, Folder 1321)
    - "K istorii vozvrashchenstva," (article), holograph, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1322)
    - "Stanislavskii," (article), clipping, 1938 (Box 57, Folder 1323)
    - Poetry, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1324)
    - Notes (Box 57, Folder 1325)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Poems by V. Luzunov, holograph, 1923 (Box 57, Folder 1326)
    - Poems by Sofiia Parnok, holograph, 1915, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1327)
    - Poems by M. Shkapskaia, typescript, 1923 (Box 57, Folder 1328)
- Materials Removed from Books, 1961-1988; Series IX; 0.25' (1 box)
  - Notes, holograph, on NNB's business card, removed from Les francs-maçons russes du XXe siècle, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1352)
    By NNB (Arles: Actes Sud, 1990).
  - Air France boarding pass removed from Brève autobiographie littéraire et autres nouvelles, n.y. Jun 15 (Box 65, Folder 1353)
    By Alberto Moravia (Paris: Salvy, 1989).
  - Russian translation by NNB, printed version, of "Lenore" by Gottfried Buerger, removed from Povelitelnitsa, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1354)
    By NNB (Berlin: Parabola, 1932).
  - Clipping of poem by NNB removed from Posliednye i pervye, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1355)
    By NNB (Paris: Isd-vo IA, 1931).
  - Ivask, IUrii. "The World of Vladimir Nabokov," printed version, removed from Song of Igor's Campaign, 1961 Apr (Box 65, Folder 1356)
    Translated by Vladimir Nabokov (New York: Vintage Books, 1960).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Vladimir Nabokov: The American Years, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1357)
    By Brian Boyd (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1991).
  - Notes, typescript mimeograph, removed from Sobranie sochinenii v chetyrekh tomakh, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1358)
    By N. Gumilev (Vashington: Izd-vo Victor Kamkin, 1968).
  - Three articles on Osip Mandelshtam removed from Collected Works, 1962-69 (Box 65, Folder 1359)
    By Osip Mandelshtam (Washington: Inter-Language Literary Associates, 1964-1969).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from C'est moi qui souligne, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1360)
    By NNB (Arles: Actes sud, 1989).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from C'est moi qui souligne, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1361)
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Sem let s Gorkim, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1362)
    By Ilia Shkapa (Moskva: Sovetskii pisatel, 1964).
  - Photocopy of inscription to NNB from Andrey Bely, annotated by NNB, removed from Stikhotvoreniia i poemy (Box 65, Folder 1363)
    By Andrey Bely (Moskva: Sovetskii pisatel, 1966).
  - Notes, holograph and note from Alexandra Pletnioff-Boutin, removed from Marina Tsvetaeva: mythe et réalité (Box 65, Folder 1364)
    By Maria Razumovsky (Montricher: Editions Noir Sur Blanc, 1988).
  - Shopping list, holograph, removed from Vospominaniia o neproshedshem vremeni, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1365)
    By R. D. Orlova (Ann Arbor: Ardis, 1983).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Sochineniia, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1366)
    By Anna Andreevna Akhmatova (Washington, D.C.: Inter-Language Literary Associates, 1965-1983).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Symbolism: Its Meaning and Effect (Box 65, Folder 1367)
    By Alfred North Whitehead (New York: Capricorn Books, 1959).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Chekhov: A Collection of Critical Essays, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1368)
    Edited by Robert Louis Jackson (Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1967).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Modern Literary Criticism: An Anthology, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1369)
    Edited by Irving Howe (New York: Grove Press, Inc., 1961).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Form and Value in Modern Poetry (Box 65, Folder 1370)
    By R. P. Blackmur (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday & Company, Inc., 1957).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from The Italics Are Mine, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1371)
    By NNB (New York: Harcourt, Brace & World, Inc., 1969).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from C'est moi qui souligne, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1372)
    By NNB (Arles: Actes Sud, 1989).
  - Cable television advertisement, with notes, holograph, removed from Kursivointi minun, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1372a)
    By NNB (Porvoo: Werner Soederstroem Osakeyhitoe, 1990).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Zheleznaia zhenshchina, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1373)
    By NNB (Moskva: Izd-vo "Knizhnaia palata," 1991).
  - Notes, holograph, on yellow paper removed, from Zheleznaia zhenshchina, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1374)
  - Notes regarding citation of source, holograph, removed from Histoire de la Baronne Boudberg, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1375)
  - Clippings regarding psychology, removed from Art and Illusion, 1969, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1376)
    By E. H. Gombrich (New York: Bollingen Foundation, 1961).
  - Photograph of unidentified nude woman, removed from Les fleurs du mal, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1377)
    By Charles Baudelaire (Paris: Les Editions G. Crès et Cie, 1925).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Complete Poems and Plays, 1909-1950 (Box 65, Folder 1378)
    By T. S. Eliot (New York: Harcourt, Brace, 1958).
  - "Some Suggestions [and] Additional Data," notes, holograph, removed from Russian Avant-Garde Art: The George Costakis Collection (Box 65, Folder 1379)
    Edited by Angelica Zander Rudenstine (New York: H. N. Abrams, 1981).
  - [List?], holograph, removed from Lichnye arkhivnye fondy v gosudarstvennykh khranilischakh SSSR (Box 65, Folder 1380)
    By Soviet Union. Glavnoe arkhivnoe upravlenie (Moskva, 1962).
  - "Summing Up Sartre" by John Weightman, clipping, with note, holograph, by NNB, removed from Being and Nothingness, 1987 Aug 13 (Box 65, Folder 1381)
    By Jean Paul Sartre (New York: Philosophical Library, 1956).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Aristotle. Selections, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1382)
    Translated by Philip Wheelwright (New York: Odyssey Press, 1951).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Quoi? l'éternité, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1383)
    By Marguerite Yourcenar (Paris: Gallimard, 1988).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Reminiscences of Alexander Blok (Box 65, Folder 1384)
    By Andrey Bely (Letchworth, Hertfordshire: Bradda Books Ltd, 1964).
  - Note, holograph, removed from Enemies of Promise and Other Essays: An Autobiography of Ideas (Box 65, Folder 1385)
    By Cyril Connolly (Garden City, NY: Anchor Books, Doubleday & Company, Inc., 1960).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Theory of Literature, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1386)
    By René Wellek and Austin Warren (New York: Harcourt, Brace, 1962).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from The Golden Ass of Apuleius: A New Translation, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1386a)
    By Robert Graves (New York: Pocket Books, Inc., 1952).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from An Arrow in the Wall: Selected Poetry and Prose, [1988] (Box 65, Folder 1387)
    By Andrei Voznesenskii (New York: H. Holt, 1987).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Anton Chekov's Life and Thought: Selected Letters and Commentary (Box 65, Folder 1388)
    Translated by Michael Henry Heim (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1975).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from La prison romantique, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1389)
    By Victor H. Brombert (Paris: J. Corti, 1975).
  - Note, holograph, removed from A Reader's Guide to T. S. Eliot, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1390)
    By George Williamson (New York: Noonday Press, 1953).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from The Human Image in Dramatic Literature (Box 65, Folder 1391)
    By Francis Fergusson (Garden City, NY: Doubleday Anchor Books, 1957).
  - Notes, holograph, removed from Khodasevich: His Life and Art (Box 65, Folder 1392)
    By David M. Bethea (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1983).
- Printed Materials, 1891-1990; Series X; 4.0' (8 boxes)
  - Actes Sud. "Catalogue", 1985 (Box 66, Folder 1393)
  - Adamovich, Georgii. [Review of Georgii Ivanov's Otplytie na ostrov T Siteru ], photocopy, [1937] (Box 66, Folder 1394)
  - Aerial Ways
    In Russian.
    - II, annotated, 1961 (Box 66, Folder 1395)
      With clipping.
    - V, annotated, 1967 (Box 66, Folder 1396)
  - "Andrei Belyi. Russian Study Series No. 51," with notes, holograph, 1965 (Box 66, Folder 1397)
  - "Andrei Belyi. Russian Study Series No. 57," annotated, 1966 (Box 66, Folder 1398)
  - Annales contemporaines, No. I-LXV, 1920-37 (Box 66, Folder 1399-1400)
    In Russian. With annotated envelope.
  - Berberova, Nina Nikolaevna
    - "Andrew Field, Nabokov: His Life in Art ," The Russian Review, 1968 Jan (Box 66, Folder 1401)
    - Astachev à Paris (Arles: Actes Sud, 1988). Brochures (Box 66, Folder 1402)
    - Borodine (Arles: Actes Sud, 1989). Brochures, n.d. (Box 66, Folder 1403)
    - "Carl R. Proffer, Keys to Lolita ," The Russian Review, 1968 Oct (Box 66, Folder 1404)
    - C'est moi qui souligne. Grands textes printed version, Revue des deux mondes, 1989 Apr (Box 67, Folder 1405)
    - "The End of the Turgenev Library," The Journal of Library History, 1981 (Box 67, Folder 1406)
    - "Notes on Nabokov's British Literary Ancestors," Canadian-American Slavic Studies, 1985 (Box 67, Folder 1407)
    - "Pauline de Rothschild, The Irrational Journey ," The Russian Review, 1968 Apr (Box 67, Folder 1408)
    - Le Roseau révolté (Arles: Actes Sud, 1988). Brochure (Box 67, Folder 1409)
    - "Sentence Commuted," printed version, The Literary Review, 1985 (Box 67, Folder 1410)
    - "Vladimir Nabokov, Speak, Memory ," The Russian Review, 1967 Oct (Box 67, Folder 1411)
    - "Vladislav Khodasevich--A Russian Poet," printed version, The Russian Review, 1952 Apr (Box 67, Folder 1412)
    - "Von Doderer i ego romany" (Box 67, Folder 1413)
    - Zheleznaia zhenshchina (New York: Russica), annotated, 1981 (Box 67, Folder 1414)
  - Boutchik, Vladimir. Bibliographie des oeuvres littéraires russes traduites en français, 1935-36 (Box 67, Folder 1415)
  - Bridges (Munich, Germany)
    - 1 (Box 68, Folder 1416)
    - 11, 1965 (Box 68, Folder 1417)
  - Chast' rechi: al'manakh literatury i iskusstva, No. 1, 1980 (Box 68, Folder 1418)
  - Dom u Nikitskikh Vorot: Putevoditel' po Muzeiu-kvaptire A.M. Gor'kogo v Moskve (Moscow: Sovetskaia Rossiia), 1987 (Box 68, Folder 1419)
  - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor. Besy (Saint Petersburg), annotated, with notes, 1891 (Box 68, Folder 1420)
  - Grani, 44, 1959 (Box 69, Folder 1421)
  - Les gutenberg du livre. Le grand livre du mois, 1990 (Box 69, Folder 1422)
  - Herodotus. The Histories translated by Aubrey de Selincourt (Penguin Books), 1955 (Box 69, Folder 1423)
  - Hughes, Robert P. "Gleb Struve: A Bibliography," annotated, 1980 (Box 69, Folder 1424)
  - Iokar, L. N. and N. M. Timofeeva. Ulitsa Vorovskogo, 25a (Moscow: Moskovskii rabochii), 1987 (Box 69, Folder 1425)
    Inscribed to NNB by Iokar.
  - Letopis' zhizni i tvorchestva, vol. 3 (A. M. Gor'kogo: Moscow), 1959 (Box 69, Folder 1426)
  - Marcus Aurelius. Meditations translated by Maxwell Staniforth (Penguin Books), 1970 (Box 70, Folder 1427)
  - Meipakh, Mikhail. [Zametki ov Anne Akhmatovoi], 1989 (Box 70, Folder 1428)
  - Muzei A. M. Gor'kogo v Moskve (Moscow: Planeta), 1987 (Box 70, Folder 1429)
    Set of individual cards, with an introduction by L. N. Iokar. Inscribed to NNB by Iokar.
  - [Muzei-kvartira A. M. Gorkogo v Moskve] (Moscow), 1979 (Box 70, Folder 1430)
  - Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich. "The Luzhin Defense," The New Yorker, 1964 (Box 70, Folder 1431-1432)
  - The New Review
    - XXXVIII, 1954 (Box 70, Folder 1433)
    - XLVIII, 1957 Mar (Box 70, Folder 1434)
    - LVIII, 1959 Sep (Box 70, Folder 1435)
    - 59, 1960 Mar (Box 70, Folder 1436)
    - 63, 1961 Mar (Box 71, Folder 1437)
    - 72, 1963 Jun (Box 71, Folder 1438)
    - 73, 1963 Sep (Box 71, Folder 1439)
    - 78, 1965 Mar (Box 71, Folder 1440)
    - 79, 1965 Jun (Box 71, Folder 1441)
    - 80, 1965 Sep (Box 72, Folder 1442)
    - 82, 1966 Mar (Box 72, Folder 1443)
    - 83, 1966 Jun (Box 72, Folder 1444)
    - 85, 1966 Dec (Box 72, Folder 1445)
  - RLT Index, 1971-76 (Box 72, Folder 1446)
  - Slavica Hierosolymitana, Vol. IV, 1979 (Box 72, Folder 1447)
  - Texas Studies in Literature and Language, Vol. XVII, 1975 (Box 73, Folder 1448)
  - TriQuarterly
    - Number seventeen, 1970 (Box 73, Folder 1448a)
    - Number twenty-seven, 1973 (Box 73, Folder 1448b)
    - Number twenty-eight, 1973 (Box 73, Folder 1448c)
  - "Ukazatel' soderzhaniia 101 knigi "Novogo zhurnala" c 1942 goda po 1970 god", n.d. (Box 73, Folder 1449)
  - Wiener Slawistischer Almanach, Band 9, 1982 (Box 73, Folder 1450)
  - Yerevan (Armenia). Guidebook to, 1969 (Box 73, Folder 1451)
  - Unidentified
    - Poems, n.d. (Box 73, Folder 1452)
      In French.
    - "Usually Destroyed" (fragment), annotated, n.d. (Box 73, Folder 1453)
- Microfilm Strips, n.d.; Series XI; 0.5' (2 boxes)
  Boxes 74 and 75, Microfilm Strips, contains cut microfilm strips and positive contact prints. This material was formerly completely restricted. The original microfilm strips remain restricted for preservation purposes; patrons are asked to use the contact prints for reference.
  - Microfilm strips, n.d. (Box 74, Folder 1456-1470)
  - Contact prints, n.d. (Box 75, Folder 1471-1485)
- Oversize, 8.0' (5 boxes, 1 bsd)
  Note Cards
  - Liudi i lozhi (in Series II), n.d. (Box 58 (Oversize))
  - Zheleznaia zhenshchina (in Series II), n.d. (Box 59 (Oversize))
  - L'Affaire Kravtchenko (French ed.). Poster (in Series II), n.d. (Box 60 (Oversize), Folder 1328a)
  - Honorary degree from Yale University, diploma (in Series IV), 1992 (Box 60 (Oversize), Folder 1329)
  - Desk Calendar (in Series IV), 1993 (Box 60 (Oversize), Folder 1330)
  - Chevalier de l'Ordre des Arts et des Lettres, certificate (in Series VI), 1989 (Box 60 (Oversize), Folder 1331)
  - Academic hoods (in Series VI), 1980-92 (Box 61 (Oversize), Folder 1332)
  - Black dress (in Series VI), n.d. (Box 62 (Oversize), Folder 1333)
  - "L'Accompagnatrice" French editions. Poster for "L'Accompagnatrice," a French film based on the story (in Series II), [1992?] (Box Bsd, folder 1333b)
- Restricted Fragile, 2.50' (2 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 63-64, Restricted Fragile. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 28, folder 731 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1334)
  - Box 38, folder 916 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1335)
  - Box 38, folder 919 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1336)
  - Box 38, folder 921 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1337)
  - Box 38, folder 923 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1338)
  - Box 38, folder 927 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1339)
  - Box 38, folder 929 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1340)
  - Box 38, folder 935 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1341)
  - Box 38, folder 936 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1342)
  - Box 38, folder 937 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1343)
  - Box 39, folder 944 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1344)
  - Box 39, folder 951 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1345)
  - Box 39, folder 953 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1346)
  - Box 39, folder 954 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1347)
  - Box 45, folder 1055 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1348)
  - Box 46, folder 1073 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1348a)
  - Box 66, folder 1395 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1454)
  - Box 66, folders 1399-1400 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1455)
  - Box 56, folder 1272 (Box 64 (Oversize), Folder 1349)
  - Box 56, folder 1273 (Box 64 (Oversize), Folder 1350)
  - Box 56, folder 1275 (Box 64 (Oversize), Folder 1351)